Now, I'm an ethnobotanist.
أنا عالم نبات أعراقي.
That's a scientist who works in the rainforest
وظيفته العمل في الغابات المطرية
to document how people use local plants.
لتوثيق طرق استخدام النباتات من قبل البشر.
I've been doing this for a long time,
مضى وقت طويل على عملي في هذا المجال
and I want to tell you,
وأردت أن آقول لكم ، أن هؤلاء الناس
these people know these forests and these medicinal treasures
يعرفون تلك الغابات وكنوزها الطبية
better than we do and better than we ever will.
أفضل منا وأكثر مما يمكننا معرفته مستقبلا.
But also, these cultures,
ولكن أيضا، تلك الثقافات،
these indigenous cultures,
تلك الثقافات الأصلية
are disappearing much faster than the forests themselves.
تتلاشى بسرعة تفوق سرعة تلاشي الغابات نفسها.
And the greatest and most endangered species
وأكثر الكائنات المعرضة للخطر
in the Amazon Rainforest
في غابات الأمازون المطرية
is not the jaguar,
ليس حيوان اليغور
it's not the harpy eagle,
وليس طائر العقاب الخطاف
it's the isolated and uncontacted tribes.
إنها القبائل المنعزلة التي لم تتصل بالبشر.
Now four years ago, I injured my foot in a climbing accident
قبل أربع سنوات، أصبت قدمي في حادثة تسلق
and I went to the doctor.
وذهبت إلى الطبيب.
She gave me heat,
عالجتني بالكمادات الحارة
she gave me cold, aspirin,
والكمادات الباردة وجرعة أسبرين
narcotic painkillers, anti-inflammatories,
وعقاقير مضادة للألم ومضادات التهاب
cortisone shots.
وحقن الكورتيزون.
It didn't work.
لم ينجح أي من ذلك.
Several months later,
لاحقا، وبعد عدة أشهر،
I was in the northeast Amazon,
كنت في شمال شرق الأمازون
walked into a village,
ومررت بقرية هناك
and the shaman said, "You're limping."
قال لي المطبب "إنك تعرج."
And I'll never forget this as long as I live.
ولن أنسى ذلك ما حييت.
He looked me in the face and he said,
نظر في عيني مباشرة وقال
He walked over to a palm tree
مشى باتجاه نخلة
and carved off a fern,
واقتطع نبتة سرخس
threw it in the fire,
وقذف بها في النار
applied it to my foot,
ثم وضعها على قدمي
threw it in a pot of water,
ووضع نفس الورقة في ماء مغلي
and had me drink the tea.
وقدم لي المنفوع لأشربه.
The pain disappeared for seven months.
اختفى الألم لسبعة أشهر.
When it came back, I went to see the shaman again.
عندما عاودني الألم ذهبت للمطبب من جديد.
He gave me the same treatment,
وقدم لي نفس العلاج
and I've been cured for three years now.
والآن شفيت تماماً منذ ثلاث سنوات.
Who would you rather be treated by?
أي طبيب معالج ستختارون؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, make no mistake — Western medicine
والآن، لا شك في أن الطب الغربي
is the most successful system of healing ever devised,
هو أنجح الانظمة التي ابتكرت للعلاج
but there's plenty of holes in it.
لكنه يعاني من ثغرات كثيرة.
Where's the cure for breast cancer?
أين علاج سرطان الثدي؟
Where's the cure for schizophrenia?
أين علاج مرض الفصام؟
Where's the cure for acid reflux?
أين علاج ارتجاع المريء (مرض غورد)؟
Where's the cure for insomnia?
أين علاج الأرق؟
The fact is that these people
والحقيقة أنّ هؤلاء البشر
can sometimes, sometimes, sometimes
قد يتمكنون أحيانا، أحيانا، أحيانا
cure things we cannot.
من علاج الأمراض التي استعصت علينا.
Here you see a medicine man in the northeast Amazon
تشاهدون هنا مطبباً في شمال شرق الأمازون
treating leishmaniasis,
يعالج داء الليشمانيا
a really nasty protozoal disease
وهو مرض طفيلي مؤذ للغاية
that afflicts 12 million people around the world.
يصاب به 12 مليون شخص حول العالم
Western treatment are injections of antimony.
يعالجه الطبّ الغربي بحقن الاثمد.
They're painful, they're expensive,
وهي مؤلمة ومكلفة
and they're probably not good for your heart;
وقد تضرّ بقلبك؛
it's a heavy metal.
أنها مصنوعة من معدن ثقيل.
This man cures it with three plants from the Amazon Rainforest.
يعالجها هذا المطبب باستخدام 3 أنواع من نباتات غابات الأمازون.
This is the magic frog.
هذا هو الضفدع السحري.
My colleague, the late great Loren McIntyre,
زميلي الراحل العظيم لورن ماكنتاير
discoverer of the source lake of the Amazon,
مكتشف منبع الأمازون،
Laguna McIntyre in the Peruvian Andes,
بحيرة ماكنتاير في جبال الأنديز بالبيرو،
was lost on the Peru-Brazil border about 30 years ago.
فُقد في المنطقة الحدودية بين البيرو والبرازيل قبل حوالي 30 عاماً.
He was rescued by a group of isolated Indians called the Matsés.
وانقاذه وقتها مجموعة من الهنود المنعزلة يعرفون بالماتسيس.
They beckoned for him to follow them into the forest, which he did.
أشاروا له بأن يتبعهم في عمق الغابة، وفعل ذلك.
There, they took out palm leaf baskets.
هناك وضعوا السلال المصنوعة من سعف النخيل.
There, they took out these green monkey frogs —
واخرجوا منها الضفادع القرديّة الخضراء —
these are big suckers, they're like this —
إنها ضفادع كبيرة الحجم —
and they began licking them.
ثمّ بدؤوا بلعقها.
It turns out, they're highly hallucinogenic.
اتضح لاحقاً بأنها تسبب الهلوسة.
McIntyre wrote about this and it was read by the editor of High Times magazine.
ماكنتاير كتب عن ذلك وقرئ مقاله محرر مجلة هاي تايمز.
You see that ethnobotanists have friends in all sorts of strange cultures.
كما ترون يملك علماء النبات العرقيين بأصدقاء من حميع الثقافات الغريبة.
This guy decided he would go down to the Amazon and give it a whirl,
قرر المحرر زيارة الأمازون وخوض التجربة.
or give it a lick, and he did, and he wrote,
أو لعقها! وهذا ما حدث بالفعل. ثمّ كتب
"My blood pressure went through the roof,
"قفز ضغط دمي للسقف،
I lost full control of my bodily functions,
فقدت قدرة التحكم بوظائف جسمي تماما
I passed out in a heap,
فقدت وعيي وسقطت مكوّماً
I woke up in a hammock six hours later,
واستيقظت على أرجوحة بعد 6 ساعات
felt like God for two days."
وشعرت بأني إله ليومين."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
An Italian chemist read this and said,
قرأ عالم كيمياء إيطالي ذلك وقال:
"I'm not really interested in the theological aspects of the green monkey frog.
"لست مهتما بالجوانب اللاهوتية للضفادع القردية الخضراء.
What's this about the change in blood pressure?"
ولكن ماذا عن التغير في ضغط الدم؟"
Now, this is an Italian chemist
والان هذا الكيميائي الإيطالي
who's working on a new treatment for high blood pressure
يعمل على علاج جديد للارتفاع ضغط الدم
based on peptides in the skin of the green monkey frog,
بناء على ببتيدات موجودة علي جلد الضفدع القردي الاخضر،
and other scientists are looking
و هناك علماء اخرون يبحثون
at a cure for drug-resistant Staph aureus.
عن علاج للعنقوديات الذهبية المقاومة للأدوية.
How ironic if these isolated Indians and their magic frog
كم سيكون مثيرا للسخرية إذا أثبت هؤلاء الهنود المنعزلين وضفادعهم السحرية
prove to be one of the cures.
أنها جزء من العلاجات.
in the northwest Amazon, in the middle of a yage ceremony.
في شمال غرب الأمازون أثناء طقوس الياهي
I took him to Los Angeles to meet a foundation officer
اصطحبته الى لوس أنجلوس ليلتقي بموظف لمؤسسة
looking for support for monies to protect their culture.
للبحث عن دعم مالي لحماية ثقافتهم.
This fellow looked at the medicine man, and he said,
نظر الموظف إلى المطبب وقال:
"You didn't go to medical school, did you?"
"لم تدرس الطب، أليس كذلك؟"
The shaman said, "No, I did not."
قال المطبب: "لا، لم أفعل."
He said, "Well, then what can you know about healing?"
قال: "حسنا، إذن ماذا تعرف عن علاج الناس؟"
The shaman looked at him and he said,
نظر المطبب إليه وقال:
"You know what? If you have an infection, go to a doctor.
"أتعلم؟ اذا اصبت بعدوى، إذهب إلى الطبيب.
Western medicine can't touch those. I cure them."
والطب الغربي عاجز عن علاجها بينما أنا أستطيع
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But all is not rosy in learning from nature about new medicines.
ولكن الطريق ليس سهلا نحو اكتشاف الأدوية الجديدة من خلال الطبيعة
This is a viper from Brazil,
هذه أفعى سامة من البرازيل،
the venom of which was studied at the Universidade de São Paulo here.
دُرِسَ سمها هنا في جامعة ساو باولو.
It was later developed into ACE inhibitors.
حيث تم تطويرها في مثبطات مستضد سرطاني مضغي.
This is a frontline treatment for hypertension.
و هذا علاج أولي لارتفاع ضغط الدم
Hypertension causes over 10 percent
إرتفاع ضغط الدم يسبب أكثر من 10%
of all deaths on the planet every day.
من حالات الوفيات يوميا في العالم.
This is a $4 billion industry
وهي صناعة بقيمة 4 مليار دولار
based on venom from a Brazilian snake,
تقوم على سم أفعى برازيلية
and the Brazilians did not get a nickel.
بينما لم يحصل البرازيليون على قرشٍ واحد.
This is not an acceptable way of doing business.
وهذه طريقة غير مقبولة للتجارة.
The rainforest has been called the greatest expression of life on Earth.
الغابات المطرية تعتبر تحفة طبيعية.
There's a saying in Suriname that I dearly love:
يقولون في سورينام التي أهواها:
"The rainforests hold answers to questions we have yet to ask."
"الغابات المطرية عندها إجابة لأسئلة لم تطرح بعد."
But as you all know, it's rapidly disappearing.
ولكن كما تعلمون فإنها تزول شيئا فشيئا.
Here in Brazil, in the Amazon,
هنا في البرازيل، في الأمازون
around the world.
حول العالم.
I took this picture from a small plane
لقد التقطت هذه الصورة من طائرة عندما كنا
flying over the eastern border of the Xingu indigenous reserve
محلقين فوق الحدود الشرقية لمحمية شنغو
in the state of Mato Grosso to the northwest of here.
في ولاية ماتو غروسو في الشمال الغربي من هنا.
The top half of the picture,
في النصف العلوي من الصورة
you see where the Indians live.
ترون موطن الهنود
The line through the middle
الخط في المنتصف
is the eastern border of the reserve.
هو الحد الشرقي للمحمية.
Top half Indians, bottom half white guys.
الهنود في النصف العلوي، ونحن في النصف السفلي.
Top half wonder drugs,
في النصف العلوي الأدوية المعجزة
bottom half just a bunch of skinny-ass cows.
بينما في النصف السفلي مجموعة من الأبقار الضعيفة
Top half carbon sequestered in the forest where it belongs,
الكربون محتبس حيث يجب أن يكون في العلوي،
bottom half carbon in the atmosphere
في النصف السفلي الكربون يتسرب إلى الجو
where it's driving climate change.
متسببا في التغير المناخي.
In fact, the number two cause
في الواقع ، السبب الثاني
of carbon being released into the atmosphere
لتسرب الكربون في الجو
is forest destruction.
هو تدمير الغابات.
But in talking about destruction,
وبالحديث عن التدمير،
it's important to keep in mind
من المهم أن نبقي في بالنا
that the Amazon is the mightiest landscape of all.
أن الأمازون أكثر الغابات إذهالا.
It's a place of beauty and wonder.
إنها مكان عجيب ورائع.
The biggest anteater in the world
أكبر آكل نمل في العالم
lives in the rain forest,
يعيش في الغابات المطرية
tips the scale at 90 pounds.
وهناك عنكبوت يزن 40 كيلوغرام.
The goliath bird-eating spider
ويسمى بالعنكبوت آكل الطيور
is the world's largest spider.
أكبر عنكبوت في العالم.
It's found in the Amazon as well.
موجود في الأمازون كذلك.
The harpy eagle wingspan is over seven feet.
العقاب المخادع يصل طول جناحيه للمترين.
And the black cayman —
وتمساح الكايمان الأسود —
these monsters can tip the scale at over half a ton.
هذه الوحوش قد يبلغ وزنها نصف طن.
They're known to be man-eaters.
ومشهورة بأنها آكلة للبشر.
The anaconda, the largest snake,
والأناكوندا أكبر الأفاعي
the capybara, the largest rodent.
وخنزير الماء أكبر القوارض.
A specimen from here in Brazil
وهناك نوع منها هنا في البرازيل
tipped the scale at 201 pounds.
يصل وزنها 90 كيلوغراماً.
Let's visit where these creatures live,
لنزر مكان عيش هذه المخلوقات
the northeast Amazon,
في شمال شرق الأمازون
home to the Akuriyo tribe.
موطن قبيلة الأكوريو.
Uncontacted peoples hold a mystical and iconic role
تلعب القبائل الغير معروفة لدينا دورا بارزا وساحرا
in our imagination.
في مخيلتنا.
These are the people who know nature best.
وهذه القبائل هميالأكثر معرفة بالطبيعة.
These are the people who truly live
وهؤلاء الناس يعيشون
in total harmony with nature.
بانسجام تام مع الطبيعة
By our standards, some would dismiss these people as primitive.
ولكننا نعتبرهم بدائيين بمعاييرنا.
"They don't know how to make fire,
"لا يستطيعون إضرام النار
or they didn't when they were first contacted."
أو أنهم لم يفعلوا ذلك عندما رأيناهم أول مرة."
But they know the forest far better than we do.
ولكنهم يعرفون الغابة أكثر منا بكثير.
The Akuriyos have 35 words for honey,
الأكوريوس لديهم 35 كلمة تطلق على العسل
and other Indians look up to them
وبعض الهنود يعتبرونهم
as being the true masters of the emerald realm.
الأسياد الفعليين لمنطقة الزمرد.
Here you see the face of my friend Pohnay.
هنا ترون صديقي بونيي.
When I was a teenager rocking out
عندما كنت يافعا
to the Rolling Stones in my hometown of New Orleans,
أهتف لفرقة رولينج ستون في نيو أورليانز
Pohnay was a forest nomad
كان بونيي متنقلا في الغابة
roaming the jungles of the northeast Amazon
باحثا في غابات شمال شرق الأمازون
in a small band, looking for game,
مع فرقة صغيرة، يبحث عن تحدي
looking for medicinal plants,
وعن نباتات طبية
looking for a wife,
وعن زوجة
in other small nomadic bands.
من مجموعات متنقلة أخرى.
But it's people like these
ولكن أشخاص مثل هؤلاء
that know things that we don't,
هم من يعرف أشياء لا نعرفها نحن
and they have lots of lessons to teach us.
ولديهم الكثير من الدروس لنتعلمها.
However, if you go into most of the forests of the Amazon,
ولكن، إذا نظرت في معظم غابات الأمازون
there are no indigenous peoples.
فإنك لن تجد سكانا أصليين.
This is what you find:
هذا ما ستجده:
rock carvings which indigenous peoples,
منحوتات صخرية استخدمها السكان الأصليون
uncontacted peoples, used to sharpen the edge of the stone axe.
الذين لم نعرفهم لشحذ أدواتهم الحجرية.
These cultures that once danced,
هذه الثقافات التي كانت ترقص
made love, sang to the gods,
وتتحاب فيما بينها، وتغني للإله
worshipped the forest,
وعبدت الغابة
all that's left is an imprint in stone, as you see here.
كلما تبقى هي رسومات على الحجر، كما ترون.
Let's move to the western Amazon,
دعونا ننتقل إلى غرب الأمازون
which is really the epicenter of isolated peoples.
وهي مركز القبائل المنعزلة.
Each of these dots represents
كل من هذه النقاط تمثل
a small, uncontacted tribe,
قبيلة صغيرة غير معروفة
and the big reveal today is we believe there are 14 or 15 isolated groups
والتصريح الكبير اليوم هو أننا نعتقد بأن هناك 14 أو 15 مجموعة قبلية منعزلة
in the Colombian Amazon alone.
فقط في الأمازون الكولومبي.
Why are these people isolated?
ولكن ما سبب اتعزال هؤلاء البشر؟
They know we exist, they know there's an outside world.
فهم يعلمون بوجودنا، ويعلمون بوجود عالم خارجي.
This is a form of resistance.
هذا شكل من أشكال المقاومة.
They have chosen to remain isolated,
لقد أختاروا أن يعزلوا أنفسهم
and I think it is their human right to remain so.
وأعتقد أن لهم الحق في ذلك.
Why are these the tribes that hide from man?
لماذا هؤلاء الناس بالذات يختبئون منا؟
Here's why.
هذا هو السبب.
Obviously, some of this was set off in 1492.
من الواضح أن البداية كانت سنة 1492.
But at the turn of the last century
ولكن في مطلع القرن الماضي
was the rubber trade.
ظهرت تجارة المطاط.
The demand for natural rubber,
الطلب على المطاط الطبيعي
which came from the Amazon,
الذي يستخرج من الأمازون
set off the botanical equivalent of a gold rush.
أشعل ما يشبه ثورة الذهب.
Rubber for bicycle tires,
المطاط من أجل إطارات الدراجات
rubber for automobile tires,
وإطارات السيارات
rubber for zeppelins.
والمناطيد.
It was a mad race to get that rubber,
كان سباقا جنونيا على المطاط،
and the man on the left, Julio Arana,
والرجل على اليسار، خوليو أرانا
is one of the true thugs of the story.
أحد أكبر السفاحين في التاريخ.
His people, his company,
أعوانه وشركته
and other companies like them
والشركات المماثلة
killed, massacred, tortured, butchered Indians
قتلت وذبحت وعذبت الهنود
like the Witotos you see on the right hand side of the slide.
كالذين ترونهم على يمين الصورة.
Even today, when people come out of the forest,
وحتى اليوم، من يخرج منهم من غابته
the story seldom has a happy ending.
في العادة لا يلقى نهاية سعيدة.
These are Nukaks. They were contacted in the '80s.
هؤلاء هم قبيلة النوكاك، عرفهم العالم في الثمانينات
Within a year, everybody over 40 was dead.
وخلال سنة مات كل من كان فوق الأربعين من العمر.
And remember, these are preliterate societies.
وتذكروا أن هؤلاء ليسوا جهلة.
The elders are the libraries.
الكبار منهم كالمكتبات.
Every time a shaman dies,
عندما يموت مطبب منهم
it's as if a library has burned down.
كأنما مكتبة كاملة احترقت.
They have been forced off their lands.
فقد أجبروا على ترك أراضيهم.
The drug traffickers have taken over the Nukak lands,
تجار المخدرات أخذوا أراضي النوكاك
and the Nukaks live as beggars
وأصبحوا متسولين
in public parks in eastern Colombia.
في الحدائق العامة شرق كولومبيا.
From the Nukak lands, I want to take you to the southwest,
من أراضي النوكاك سآخذكم إلى الجنوب الغربي،
to the most spectacular landscape in the world:
إلى أكثر الأماكن جمالا:
Chiribiquete National Park.
حديقة شريبيكيت الوطنية.
It was surrounded by three isolated tribes
وكانت محاطة بثلاث قبائل منعزلة
and thanks to the Colombian government and Colombian colleagues,
وبفضل حكومة كولومبيا والزملاء الكولومبيين
it has now expanded.
تمت توسعتها.
It's bigger than the state of Maryland.
والآن هي أكبر من ولاية ميرلاند.
It is a treasure trove of botanical diversity.
إنها كنز دفين من التنوع النباتي.
It was first explored botanically in 1943
استكشفت نباتيا في 1943
by my mentor, Richard Schultes,
بواسطة مرشدي رتشارد شولتيز
seen here atop the Bell Mountain,
ترونه هنا وهو على قمة جبل بيل
the sacred mountains of the Karijonas.
الجبل المقدس عند الكاريهوناس.
And let me show you what it looks like today.
ودعوني أريكم كيف تبدو اليوم.
Flying over Chiribiquete,
من فوق حديقة شيريبيكيت
realize that these lost world mountains are still lost.
هذه الجبال المفقودة ما تزال خفية.
No scientist has been atop them.
لم يصعد إليها عالم من قبل.
In fact, nobody has been atop the Bell Mountain
في الواقع لم يصعد أحد لقمة جبل بيل
since Schultes in '43.
منذ أن قام بذلك شولتيز سنة 1943.
And we'll end up here with the Bell Mountain
وسنتوقف هنا عند جبل بيل
just to the east of the picture.
في الجانب الشرقي للصورة.
Let me show you what it looks like today.
دعوني أريكم كيف يبدو اليوم.
Not only is this a treasure trove of botanical diversity,
وهو ليس مجرد كنز دفين ذو تنوع نباتي
not only is it home to three isolated tribes,
أو موطنا لثلاث قبائل منعزلة
but it's the greatest treasure trove
ولكنه أعظم كنز دفين
of pre-Colombian art in the world:
للفن ما قبل كولومبيا في العالم:
over 200,000 paintings.
بما يزيد على 200,000 رسم.
The Dutch scientist Thomas van der Hammen
وقد وصفها العالم الهولندي توماس فان دير هامن
described this as the Sistine Chapel of the Amazon Rainforest.
بأنها ككنيسة سيستينا في غابات الأمازون.
But move from Chiribiquete down to the southeast,
دعونا نذهب مجددا إلى الجنوب الشرقي من حديقة شيريبيكيت
again in the Colombian Amazon.
في الأمازون الكولومبي.
Remember, the Colombian Amazon is bigger than New England.
وتذكروا أن الأمازون الكولومبي أكبر من نيو إنجلاند.
The Amazon's a big forest,
الأمازون غابة كبيرة
and Brazil's got a big part of it,
وجزء كبير منها يقع في البرازيل
but not all of it.
ولكن ليست بالكامل.
Moving down to these two national parks,
دعونا ننتقل إلى
Cahuinari and Puré
الحديقتين الوطنيتين كاهيناري وبوريه
in the Colombian Amazon —
في الأمازون الكولومبي —
that's the Brazilian border to the right —
هذه حدود البرازيل على اليمين —
it's home to several groups
إنه موطن لمجموعات متعددة
of isolated and uncontacted peoples.
من القبائل المنعزلة والغير معروفة.
To the trained eye, you can look at the roofs
العين المدربة يمكن أن ترى أسطح
of these malocas, these longhouses,
المنازل والأبنية
and see that there's cultural diversity.
فتشاهد تنوعا ثقافي.
These are, in fact, different tribes.
هذه في الواقع قبائل مختلفة.
As isolated as these areas are,
بالرغم من انعزال هذه المناطق
let me show you how the outside world is crowding in.
سأريكم كيف يحيط بها العالم الخارجي.
Here we see trade and transport increased in Putumayo.
هنا نرى زيادة في حركة التجارة والنقل في بوتومايو.
With the diminishment of the Civil War in Colombia,
مع انتهاء الحرب الأهلية في كولومبيا،
the outside world is showing up.
بدأت تجذب أنظار العالم الخارجي.
To the north, we have illegal gold mining,
لدينا من الشمال التنقيب الغير قانوني عن الذهب
also from the east, from Brazil.
ومن الغرب، من البرازيل،
There's increased hunting and fishing for commercial purposes.
هناك تزايد للصيد التجاري للسمك والحيوانات.
We see illegal logging coming from the south,
نرى قطع الأشجار الغير قانوني من الجنوب
and drug runners are trying to move through the park
وتجار المخدرات يحاولون العبور عبر الحديقة
and get into Brazil.
للوصول إلى البرازيل.
This, in the past, is why you didn't mess
لهذا السبب لم يكن أحد يجرؤ
with isolated Indians.
على العبث مع الهنود المنعزلين.
And if it looks like this picture is out of focus
وإذا لم تكن هذه الصورة واضحة
because it was taken in a hurry, here's why.
فلإنها التقطت على عجل، وهذا هو السبب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This looks like — (Applause)
تبدو وكأنها — (تصفيق)
This looks like a hangar from the Brazilian Amazon.
يبدو كأنه عنبر في الأمازون البرازيلي.
This is an art exhibit in Havana, Cuba.
هذا معرض فني في هافانا - كوبا.
A group called Los Carpinteros.
مجموعة اسمها لوس كاربينتيروس.
This is their perception of why you shouldn't mess with uncontacted Indians.
هذه رؤيتهم عن سبب عدم العبث مع هؤلاء الهنود.
But the world is changing.
ولكن العالم يتغير.
These are Mashco-Piros on the Brazil-Peru border
هؤلاء هم ماشكو-بيروس على الحدود البرازيلية والبيروفية
who stumbled out of the jungle
وقد غادروا الغابة
because they were essentially chased out
لأنهم طوردوا
by drug runners and timber people.
من قبل تجار المخدرات وجامعي الخشب.
And in Peru, there's a very nasty business.
وفي البيرو يوجد عمل سيء
It's called human safaris.
يدعى بسفاري الإنسان.
They will take you in to isolated groups to take their picture.
حيث يأخذونك إلى تلك القبائل لالتقاط الصور.
Of course, when you give them clothes, when you give them tools,
بطبيعة الحال عندما نعطيهم ملابس وأدوات
you also give them diseases.
فإنك ننقل لهم الأمراض.
We call these "inhuman safaris."
يجب أن نسميها "السفاري اللاإنساني"
These are Indians again on the Peru border,
هؤلاء أيضا هنود على حدود البيرو
who were overflown by flights sponsored by missionaries.
يطير فوقهم الناس في رحلات ينظمها مبشرون.
They want to get in there and turn them into Christians.
يريدون جعلهم يعتنقون المسيحية.
We know how that turns out.
وكلنا يعلم كيف تنتهي الأمور.
What's to be done?
ولكن ماذا نفعل نحن؟
Introduce technology to the contacted tribes,
علينا أن نقدم التكنولوجيا للقبائل المعروفة
not the uncontacted tribes,
وليس إلى غير المعروفة
in a culturally sensitive way.
آخذين ثقافتهم بعين الاعتبار.
This is the perfect marriage of ancient shamanic wisdom
هذا هو التزاوج المثالي بين الطب التقليدي عندهم
and 21st century technology.
وتكنولوجيا القرن الواحد والعشرين.
We've done this now with over 30 tribes,
قمنا بذلك مع أكثر من 30 قبيلة
mapped, managed and increased protection
وضعنا الخرائط وقمنا بحماية وإدارة ما يزيد
of over 70 million acres of ancestral rainforest.
عن 70 مليون فدان من الغابات القديمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So this allows the Indians to take control
وهذا يسمح للهنود بالتحكم
of their environmental and cultural destiny.
بمحيطهم ومستقبلهم الثقافي.
They also then set up guard houses
وقد قاموا أيضا ببناء بيوت حراسة
to keep outsiders out.
لحماية أنفسهم من المتطفلين.
These are Indians, trained as indigenous park rangers,
هؤلاء هنود مدربون على حماية
patrolling the borders
وحراسة ومراقبة الحدود
and keeping the outside world at bay.
ودفع العالم الخارجي عنهم.
This is a picture of actual contact.
هذه صورة لتواصل فعلي.
These are Chitonahua Indians
هؤلاء هم هنود شيتوناهوا
on the Brazil-Peru border.
على حدود البرازيل والبيرو.
They've come out of the jungle
خرجوا من الغابات
asking for help.
طالبين المساعدة.
They were shot at,
وأطلق عليهم النار
their malocas, their longhouses, were burned.
وحرقت بيوتهم وأبنيتهم.
Some of them were massacred.
وذبح بعضهم.
Using automatic weapons to slaughter uncontacted peoples
ويعد استخدام أسلحة أوتوماتيكية بهدف القضاء على قبائل غير معروفة
is the single most despicable and disgusting human rights abuse
أكثر انتهاكات حقوق الإنسان فظاعةً
on our planet today, and it has to stop.
في عالمنا اليوم وبالتالي يجب وضع حد لهذا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But let me conclude by saying,
ودعوني أختم الحديث بقولي
this work can be spiritually rewarding,
عملنا هذا يرضي على الصعيد الروحي
but it's difficult and it can be dangerous.
ولكنه صعب وخطير
Two colleagues of mine passed away recently
اثنان من زملائي قضوا مؤخرا
in the crash of a small plane.
في حادث طائرة صغيرة.
They were serving the forest
كانوا يقومون بخدمة الغابة
to protect those uncontacted tribes.
لحماية القبائل الغير معروفة.
So the question is, in conclusion,
والسؤال في الختام هو:
is what the future holds.
ماذا يحمل المستقبل؟
These are the Uray people in Brazil.
هؤلاء قوم يوراي في البرازيل.
What does the future hold for them,
ماذا يحمل المستقبل لهم؟
and what does the future hold for us?
وماذا يحمل المستقبل لنا؟
Let's think differently.
عونا نفكر بطريقة مختلفة.
Let's make a better world.
لنصنع عالما أفضل.
If the climate's going to change,
إذا كان المناخ سيتغير
let's have a climate that changes for the better rather than the worse.
لنجعله يتغير للأفضل بدلا من الأسوء.
Let's live on a planet
دعونا نعش في عالم
full of luxuriant vegetation,
مليء بنباتات مزدهرة
in which isolated peoples
حيث يبقى السكان المنعزلون
can remain in isolation,
في عزلتهم،
can maintain that mystery
ويحافظون على هذه السرية
and that knowledge
وتلك المعرفة
if they so choose.
إن أرادوا ذلك.
Let's live in a world
دعونا نعش في عالم
where the shamans live in these forests
حيث يعيش المطببين في هذه الغابات
and heal themselves and us
ويعالجون أنفسهم ونحن
with their mystical plants
بنباتاتهم السحرية
and their sacred frogs.
وضفادعهم المقدسة.
Thanks again.
شكرا مجددا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)